<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-05-23T14:10:07-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">kabtonnetworks</title><subtitle>Put your heart, mind, and soul into even your smallest acts. This is the secret of success. -Swami Sivananda
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Winning from Within</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/book-review/2017/05/22/winningfromwithin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winning from Within" /><published>2017-05-22T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/book-review/2017/05/22/winningfromwithin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/book-review/2017/05/22/winningfromwithin.html">&lt;h1&gt;Winning From Within - Erica Ariel Fox&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her book, Erica Fox outlines methods that can be used to find our ‘center’ and be better in our reaction to life’s situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Listen to your mother. A meal becomes good by starting with quality instructions. It becomes great when you add a quality chef.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She mentions that knowing the rules, and what to do isn’t enough when you are faced with life’s situations, as there are many people who know what to do, but don’t follow it when faced with a situation that requires them to act.
Fox introduces the concept of the performance gap, which describes how people approach a situation, any situation, in life. In many people’s minds, there is an ideal way of how they see themselves acting in a situation. But there is also the actual way in which they act in this situation; In the heat of the moment when one doesn’t have time to think about recipes. The difference between your ideal way of approaching a situation and your actual way is called the performance gap. The greater this difference, the bigger the performance gap. The smaller this difference, the smaller the performance gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closing the performance gap is the desirable outcome as it means we have found our center and we are acting how we truly want to. She also posits that rules are not enough to close the performance gap; We need to take the time out to become quality chefs.
We become quality chefs by examining the factors at our core that are responsible for how we act the way we do. Fox refers to these as the big four. There are certain qualities, or archetypes, that seem to be at play in most individuals and are exuded to varying degrees. These qualities come naturally to people and aren’t necessarily consciously learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fox mentions that although there might be an inexhaustible list of qualities, there are four main ones that seem to be central to the individual. These are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Dreamer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Thinker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Lover&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Warrior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the corporate executive as an analogy, She likens the dreamer to the CEO, who is responsible for thinking about the ‘big picture’ and general direction of his company. He imagines what the future will be like and how his company can take advantage of it. The thinker is the chief financial operator. The CFO is concerned with the analysis and the logistics concerned with keeping the company financially viable. The lover is the VP- head of human resources. This Lover is concerned with caring for people and seeing how people can amicably work together in the interest of the company while being fulfilled. The warrior is the chief operating officer. The CFO is the person who makes things work. This person is not afraid to get his hands dirty and does what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wait, there’s more…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These qualities are what constitutes the human ego. As individuals, we use the big four to varying degrees and we tend to lean toward 1 or 2 qualities while neglecting or failing to utilize the others. This probably happens because of how we were socialized as children. We tend to also develop a ‘picture’ of ourselves during this socialization process, which cements our favorite qualities of the big 4. Fox posits that a big step toward closing the performance gap is understanding these 4 qualities and striving to use them in equal proportions when approached with life’s situations. She also mentions that there might be times when we need to have a sort of negotiation process among the qualities as the situation demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She further states that in western cultures, the big 4 tends to be conflated and placed on a pedestal as the entirety of the individual. She, however, refutes this and says that while they are an integral part of the individual, there is, in fact, more than the big 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Meet the directors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the corporate executives, the big 4 is in need of a group of mature, dispassionate persons who are able to look beyond their noses and provide wisdom and foster a culture of circumspectness. Fox refers to these as the transformers. There are 3 main transformers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Lookout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Captain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Voyager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lookout is responsible for ensuring that you are connected to your center of well-being, which is the state in which you are one with the internal self and the external self. This director is also responsible for monitoring the big four, taking in information through an unbiased lens, and passing it on to his fellow director. The captain is responsible for taking internal information about the big 4 from the lookout and also taking information from the outside. The multiplicity of his information sources enables the captain to utilize the big four in the most balanced and effective way, while drawing from your values and wisdom contained in your center, to get desired results. The Voyager is concerned with growth. He charts a path where no path has been before and is always moving ahead, regardless of failures or setbacks. The Voyager keeps on moving and realizes that a richer inner life and outer life is integral to his success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winning from within gives us insight into how we can become better at handling the plethora of situations that flood us daily in our fast-paced world. It also awakens us to the possibilities of growth and new frontiers waiting to be explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;dcomment&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:70px;&quot;&gt; 

 

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;

/**
*  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
*  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables*/
/*
var disqus_config = function () {
this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
};
*/
(function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
s.src = '//kabtonnetworks.disqus.com/embed.js';
s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
(d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
})();
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

 

&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">Winning From Within - Erica Ariel Fox</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ich bin fünfundzwanzig</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/life/2016/12/19/ich-bin-funfundzwanzig.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ich bin fünfundzwanzig" /><published>2016-12-19T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-19T16:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/life/2016/12/19/ich-bin-funfundzwanzig</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/life/2016/12/19/ich-bin-funfundzwanzig.html">&lt;p&gt;Ah… The big 2 &amp;amp; 5. Quarter of a century upon this place we call earth. The past 25 years have taught me so many lessons and I think I have experienced tremendous growth in most areas of my life because of these lessons. The past year has taught me some particularly difficult lessons; so many things have transpired in this relatively short time span that will permanently change my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the year, I was diagnosed with multiple sclerosis (ms). The news of this diagnosis hit like a ten-tonne brick. I kept asking myself, why I, a young man from Jamaica (where this disease is extremely rare and next to unheard of) with a relatively healthy lifestyle, would be struck with such misfortune. It was an extremely difficult thing for my family and me to accept and it could be said that we went through a grieving process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, there were moments of extreme despondency and hopelessness. If you are particularly close to me, you’ll know that I am the ‘great adumbrator’. I like to plan my life out in great detail, and have goals and milestones to achieve; for the most part, I have achieved most of the goals I set for myself. But reminiscing over the past year, I would define myself as a naval captain who has had 24 years of experience. However, all those years have been spent in relatively calm waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a young naval student, you learnt about phenomena called ‘storms’ and ‘rough seas’ and their ability to sink your ship, but for 24 years you’ve never really seen these ‘storms’ your instructors or fellow captains would tell you about. So you navigate anyway with great successes and accomplishments, and all your plans at sea always seem to deterministically work out. You grow bolder, and become more confident in your abilities. Then one day the unexpected happens (no plans, yikes!): A storm comes. Your safe, majestic, floating cocoon sinks and you are forced to swim, or drown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such has been life with ms. It is not something you plan for or expect (as with many other diseases), but it definitely tips your boat and you have to decide if you want to swim or drown. Swimming can be difficult and extremely tiring, especially for someone who doesn’t regularly swim, but it gets easier with time. After enough swimming you find that the muscles in your hands and feet have gotten bigger and stronger and much less effort is required than before. On days when you do not feel like swimming, you still have to swim (or drown). But on other days you might luckily find a floating object to support you or even a dolphin on whose back you can coast along!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience has taught me some other lessons which I think are very valuable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;1. Divide and Conquer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persons with ms will know that a great number of physical challenges are associated with the disease. This might not become apparent to persons without the disease unless the person being challenged is relegated to a bed or a wheelchair (which can be frustrating at times, but that is for another time). There are, however, a lot of others with the disease (like me) who are not confined to a wheelchair or a bed, who can do physical things other ‘normal’ persons do. However, with one caveat– we most likely, will not be able to do it for as long or with the same speed and intensity. You will find a person with ms having to take frequent breaks while engaging in physical activities, even in activities as simple as standing. This is where the concept of dividing and conquering becomes useful to a person with ms. It is better to tackle a task or problem piece by piece with little breaks in-between. By doing this, you have greater endurance because you are not exhausting yourself by tackling the problem or task in one-fell-swoop. Additionally, the problem is solved or the task is done with a higher quality because each part is approached with great intensity while allowing for rest after, to go on to the next segment with ‘fresh eyes’ or a somewhat renewed strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept does not only work for persons with ms, but for everybody and it can be applied to most, if not all, problems life throws at us. Remember, the race is not necessarily for the swift, but for those who can endure and Rome wasn’t built in a day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;2. Be a little selfish&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to know the power and effectiveness of the word ‘no’. We are finite beings. We have a finite amount of energy to expend on daily tasks. Therefore, it is important to realize when to cease the giving of energy by simply saying no to all things and persons that will deplete your energy to dangerously low levels. I am of the opinion that it is important to ensure that you are strong enough to be of help to others because a physically or mentally depleted person will be useful to no one. So in that sense, be selfish, do you, cater to yourself and be sure that you are strong enough to help others while remembering that you will not be able to please everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;3. Cherish now&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tend to spend so much time in the past, thinking about what could be or what was and too much time in the future, thinking about what will be; while forgetting about now and what can be done now. It is of no use to dwell on the past because it is just a memory and it is unchangeable. It is also of little use to dwell on the future because it is just a figment of the imagination. The only directly controllable point in time we have is now. We decide our destiny by what we choose to do now, at this very moment. You’re choosing to be a more resilient person now by reading this post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Rihanna aptly sang:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Tomorrow’s way too far away
And we can’t get back yesterday
But we young right now
We got right now
So get up right now
‘Cause all we got is right now”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;4. Always reach forward&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is extremely  important to have a goal to strive toward. Something to swim to. It is a goal that gives life purpose and a sense of direction.
Do not ever get too fearful and steeped in uncertainty, so as to stop dreaming and reaching forward. There are few things more toxic to humankind than a person who finds solace in a state of stasis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;5. Practice an attitude of gratitude&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept has kept me afloat on my darkest days. I have realized that you cannot remain despondent if you are grateful. Being grateful promotes a sense of humility and gives your life meaningful perspective. Being grateful allows you to realize how small your problems are compared to other peoples’ problems. Being grateful makes you realize that despite the negative things you might be grappling with, there are also positive things to celebrate too. In my opinion, life is neither all good nor all bad. There is always something good to be thankful for and  something bad to be stronger from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To life, prosperity and strength for 2017!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;dcomment&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:70px;&quot;&gt; 

 

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;

/**
*  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
*  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables*/
/*
var disqus_config = function () {
this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
};
*/
(function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
s.src = '//kabtonnetworks.disqus.com/embed.js';
s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
(d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
})();
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

 

&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">Ah… The big 2 &amp;amp; 5. Quarter of a century upon this place we call earth. The past 25 years have taught me so many lessons and I think I have experienced tremendous growth in most areas of my life because of these lessons. The past year has taught me some particularly difficult lessons; so many things have transpired in this relatively short time span that will permanently change my life.</summary></entry></feed>
